<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5727 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5727.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5111 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5111.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3427 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3427.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-campbell-art-rfc5727-update-00" ipr="trust200902" updates="5727">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="SIP-Change Update">Improving the Organizational Flexibility
	of the SIP Change Process.</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

	    <author fullname="Ben Campbell" initials="B." role="editor"
	     surname="Campbell">
	      <organization>Oracle</organization>
	      <address>
	        <phone></phone>
	        <email>ben@nostrum.com</email>
	<!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
	      </address>
	    </author>
        <author fullname="ALissa Cooper" initials="A." surname="Cooper">
			<organization>Cisco</organization>
			<address>
				<phone/>
				<email>alcoop@cisco.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>	
        <author fullname="Barry Leiba" initials="B." surname="Leiba">
			<organization>Huawei</organization>
			<address>
				<phone/>
				<email>barryleiba@computer.org</email>
			</address>
		</author>	

    <date month="May" year="2015" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Applications and Real-Time</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>dispatch RAI ART sip-change</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>RFC 5727 defines several processes for the Real-time Applications and
	     Infrastructure (RAI) area. These processes include the evolution
	     of the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) and related protocols, 
	     as well as the operation of the DISPATCH and SIPCORE working groups.
		 This document updates RFC 5727 to allow flexibility for the area
		 and working group structure, while preserving the SIP change processes.
		It also generalizes the DISPATCH working group processes so that they
		can be easily adopted by other working groups.
	 </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	<t>
		<xref target="RFC5727" /> describes processes for evolving and maintaining
		the <xref target="RFC3261" > Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</xref> and related
		technologies in the Real-time Application and Infrastructure (RAI) area.
	    These processes are collectively known as the "SIP Change Process".  
	</t>
	<t> 
		At the time of this writing, the Internet Engineering Steering Group 
		(IESG) expects to reorganize the RAI area. While areas do not normally 
		have "charters" per se, RFC 5727 
		has effectively served as a charter for RAI.  The language 
		in RFC 5727 is tightly bound to the area and to the the DISPATCH
		and SIPCORE working groups.  This
		document updates RFC 5727 to remove its dependency on RAI and its working
		group structure. 
	</t>	

	<t>
		RFC 5727 specifies that the DISPATCH working group assesses potential new
		work for the area, and determines where such work should occur. DISPATCH does
		not itself take on such new work. The SIPCORE working group is responsible
		for maintenance of SIP. Other RAI working groups develop extensions to SIP that do
		not change the core protocol, new applications of SIP, and other technologies
		for interactive communication among humans.	This document further
		generalizes the processes of the DISPATCH working group so that they can be
		applied to other areas, or to clusters of technologies within an area.	
	</t>
	<t>	
		While the reorganization is expected to involve merging RAI with
		the Applications (APP) area and renaming the resulting area, the updates in
		this document do not depend on that. Rather, the authors seek to future-proof
		the SIP Change Process against future reorganizations. 
	</t>
	<t>
		This document does not change any other aspect of RFC 5727. While areas and
		working groups may change over time, the rules and procedures for changing SIP
		and other RAI protocols remain the same, until such time that they are 
		updated by 
	    future documents.
	</t>
    </section>
<section title="Dispatch-Style Working Groups">
	<t>
		The DISPATCH working group has proven successful at managing new work for 
		the RAI area. Areas may choose to adopt DISPATCH-like procedures, either for
		an entire area, or for technology-clusters in an area or across areas.
		A "Dispatch-Style" working group operates according to procedures
		similar to those used for DISPATCH.
	</t>
	<t>The "Dispatch Style" includes the following essential elements:
		<list style="symbols">
			<t>
				The working group evaluates proposals for new work for an area, or
				for a well-defined technology cluster. It acts as a filter for
				the area or cluster to determine whether a proposal is a reasonable
	            use of or addition to associated technologies. This determination 
				may depend upon established
	            criteria (for example, the SIP Change Process), the experience and
	            expertise of the participants, or a combination of the two.
			</t>
			<t>
				The dispatch-style working group determines an appropriate venue
				for the work.
				The venue could be an existing working group. If no appropriate
				group exist, it may develop a charter for a BoF, a new working
				group, or an <xref target="RFC5111"> exploratory group</xref>. 
				The working group may also determine that a proposal should not
				be acted upon at the time. 
			</t>
			<t>
				The dispatch-style working group does not complete the proposed work.
				It may, however, adopt milestones needed to properly dispatch the work.
				For example, it may produce charter text for a BoF or a new
				working group, an initial problem statement, or documentation
				about why certain work was not pursued. 			 
			</t>	
		</list>
	</t>
	<t>
		Nothing in this list prevents existing working groups from directly 
		adopting
		new work that reasonably fits their charters. For borderline cases,
		the decision whether new work should start in a dispatch-style  group,
		or in an existing group is a judgement call among the responsible
		Area Directors and chairs. Likewise, in cases where an area has multiple
		dispatch-style groups for different purposes or technology clusters, the
		decision about which group will handle a particular proposal is a
		judgement call.
	</t>
	<t>
	    The charter of a dispatch-style group should make that fact clear, either
	    by referencing this document, or by directly describing similar procedures.
	</t>
</section>
<section title="Decoupling the SIP-Change Process from the RAI Area">
     <t>
     	This document clarifies that the SIP Change Process is not bound to
		any particular area or working group structure. All references to
		the RAI area in RFC 5727 should be interpreted as "the cluster
		of SIP and closely related application and infrastructure technologies, 
		as well as other technologies designed primarily for interactive 
		communication among humans."
	 </t>
	 <t>
	 	While the DISPATCH and SIPCORE working groups are expected to continue
	    in their current capacities, nothing in the SIP Change Process prevents
		their responsibilities from being assigned to other working groups
		in the future. 
	 </t>
	 <t>
	 	All other aspects of the SIP-Change process are to continue as described
		in RFC 5727.
	 </t>
 </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no requests to IANA.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
		This document discusses the roles and responsibilities of areas 
		and working groups. It does not create new security considerations
		in the conventional sense. 
	</t>
	<t>
		However, organizational structures come with their own security
		   considerations.  A dispatch-stye working group has the potential to
		   concentrate the control of work for an area or cluster in the hands
		   of a much smaller set of people than those in the whole area or
		   cluster.  This could have the effect of a "Denial of Service Attack"
		   against the area or cluster.  Likewise, such a concentration could
		   reduce the quality of decisions about new work. Care must be
		   taken to avoid this risk. The best mitigation is active participation
		   in the group by as many people in the area or cluster as possible.
	  </t>
		
    </section>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>
		The authors would like to thank all the previous authors of the SIP Change
		Process for their contributions. Jon Peterson, Cullen Jennings, and Robert
		Sparks authored RFC 5727. That RFC obsoleted <xref target="RFC3427"/>, which
		was in turn
		written by Allison Mankin, Scott Bradner, Rohan Mahy, Dean Willis, Brian
		Rosen, and Joerg Ott.
	</t>
	<t>
		The authors additionally thank the present and past chairs of DISPATCH
		and SIPCORE, as well as all the participants in the RAI area since its
		inception.
	</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      &RFC5727;
    </references>
<references title="Informative Reverences">
	 &RFC3261;
	 &RFC5111;
	 &RFC3427;
</references>
  </back>
</rfc>
